<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>LeiosLabs</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2022-04-01T12:18:57+02:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>James Schloss</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
  <entry>
   <title>About me</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/about"/>
   <updated>2022-03-31T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/about</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The goal of Leios Labs is to do high-quality, computational research and communicate this research as effectively as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;about-james-schloss-leios&quot;&gt;About James Schloss (Leios)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James Schloss finished his PhD at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://admissions.oist.jp/&quot;&gt;Okinawa Institute of Science and Technology&lt;/a&gt; in December of 2019 before working at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mit.edu/&quot;&gt;MIT&lt;/a&gt; for a year on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://clima.caltech.edu/&quot;&gt;Climate Machine&lt;/a&gt; project.
He is also in charge of an online repository of Algorithms known as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.algorithm-archive.org/&quot;&gt;Arcane Algorithm Archive&lt;/a&gt; and runs the youtube channel &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/c/LeiosOS/&quot;&gt;LeiosLabs&lt;/a&gt; with 85,000 subscribers along with it’s corresponding &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitch.tv/leioslabs&quot;&gt;twitch stream&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For his PhD, James focused primarily on GPGPU computing by solving the NonLinear Schrodinger Equation (also called the Gross-Pitaevskii Equation, GPE) on the GPU by building the package &lt;a href=&quot;https://gpue-group.github.io/&quot;&gt;GPUE&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the CLIMA project, James focused on Heterogeneous computing with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/JuliaGPU/KernelAbstractions.jl&quot;&gt;KernelAbstractions.jl&lt;/a&gt; package and implementing it into a large climate simulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Algorithm Archive has the impossible goal of creating an online textbook that rivals Numerical Recipes in every programming language.
This is done with the help of a community of individuals that help curate all the languages.
At the current time, the Algorithm Archive focuses on methods that are relevant to James’s research that are not adequately explained elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Twitch and Youtube, James focuses on explaining research topics with a current focus on computational creativity.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
 
  <entry>
   <title>Projects</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/projects"/>
   <updated>2022-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/projects</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;current-projects&quot;&gt;Current projects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I currently tend towards projects that are significantly technical while also providing unique and interesting visuals to easily communicate what I am doing to a general audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fae&quot;&gt;The Fractal Animation Engine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#some&quot;&gt;The Summer of Math Exposition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#aaa&quot;&gt;The Arcane Algorithm Archive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#yt&quot;&gt;Youtube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#twitch&quot;&gt;Twitch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#scribbleios&quot;&gt;Scribbleios&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recent-projects&quot;&gt;Recent projects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My most recent, concluded projects include computational science projects, such as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#clima&quot;&gt;The Climate Machine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#gpue&quot;&gt;GPUE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;all-projects&quot;&gt;All Projects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;fae&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-fractal-animation-engine&quot;&gt;The Fractal Animation Engine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/fae_banner.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fae Banner&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been increasingly interested in the meshless generation of physical fields.
By this, I mean that I want to simulate something like turbulent flow with a domain expressed analytically.
Take, for example, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.algorithm-archive.org/contents/IFS/IFS.html&quot;&gt;Iterated Function System&lt;/a&gt;.
With this, we can express an image (such as the Sierpinski triangle or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.algorithm-archive.org/contents/barnsley/barnsley.html&quot;&gt;Barnsely Fern&lt;/a&gt;); however, it is generally possible to express &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; image with the right set of equations.
It is also possible to combine iterated function systems together into a larger function system known as a fractal flame.
In principle, if we want to express any field, we can use a form of machine learning or optimal control to select an appropriate function system that approximates our field and then use the field directly for our simulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, my current research goal is to create an animation engine that can express objects entirely on a function system instead of with meshes.
This is almost certainly slower than raytracing, but comes with advantages in animation and smear frames for 3D rendering as all objects can now move via &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.algorithm-archive.org/contents/affine_transformations/affine_transformations.html&quot;&gt;affine transformations&lt;/a&gt;.
It also allows me to test the waters a bit and learn what the challenges will be in using fractals for real physics simulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 2 central challenges to this work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The generation of the &lt;em&gt;fractal code&lt;/em&gt; (the set of equations to represent a domain). The problem here is that there are not strong constraints on what the questions can be, so optimal control techniques will take a long time. When a similar project was attempted with fractal compression, the compression step took orders of magnitude longer than JPEG.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The generation of the field from the fractal code. This is challenging to do in parallel as most resources require using a chaos game to solve the iterated function system. Chaos games are (surprise) iterative methods that do not scale well on the GPU.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code is currently available &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and uses &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;KernelAbstractions.jl&lt;/a&gt; to provide parallelization on both the CPU and GPU.
As it is an ongoing project, please keep in mind that the code will be a bit rough around the edges.
For this project, I need strong symbolic computation along with parallel methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;some&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-summer-of-math-exposition&quot;&gt;The Summer of Math Exposition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/some_logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;SoME1 Banner&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Summer of Math Exposition was an online competition in collaboration with the popular youtube channel &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/c/3blue1brown&quot;&gt;3Blue1Brown&lt;/a&gt; to inspire more people to create math content online.
We asked every entrant to make something to be judged by us.
In total, there were over 1,000 valid entries, so the judging happened in 2 stages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A peer review stage where all entries judged all other entries using a system known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/leios/gavel&quot;&gt;Gavel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A manual judging phase of the top 100 entries by myself, Grant, and a few other chosen individuals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We asked for direct feedback at the end of the summer and the response was overwhelmingly positive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;aaa&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-arcane-algorithm-archive&quot;&gt;The Arcane Algorithm Archive&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.algorithm-archive.org/&quot;&gt;Arcane Algorithm Archive&lt;/a&gt; is an online textbook I am writing along with my community.
The goal is to discuss arcane algorithms that are important but not thoroughly discussed elsewhere.
I focus on the initial chapters and algorithm implementations in Julia while the community helps curate all other languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;yt&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;youtube&quot;&gt;Youtube&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/c/LeiosOS&quot;&gt;youtube channel&lt;/a&gt; currently has over 85,000 subscribers and focuses on explaining complicated topics in a simple way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;twitch&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;twitch&quot;&gt;Twitch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stream my research on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitch.tv/leioslabs&quot;&gt;twitch&lt;/a&gt; as I feel it is important to open up the process to as many people as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;scribbleios&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;scribbleios&quot;&gt;Scribbleios&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a more creative project where I write a short story and post it on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scribbleios.com/&quot;&gt;scribbleios&lt;/a&gt;.
It’s just a way to get my creative juices flowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;clima&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-climate-machine&quot;&gt;The Climate Machine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://clima.caltech.edu/&quot;&gt;Climate Machine&lt;/a&gt; is an attempt to make a new climate simulation engine to provide more accurate simulation results.
I worked on the project in 2020 and primarily focused on teaching fundamentals of GPGPU and providing support for heterogeneous computing via the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/JuliaGPU/KernelAbstractions.jl&quot;&gt;KernelAbstractions.jl&lt;/a&gt; package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;GPUE&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;gpue&quot;&gt;GPUE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/projects/gpue_logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;GPUE logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://clima.caltech.edu/&quot;&gt;GPUE&lt;/a&gt; is the GPU-based Gross-Pitaevskii Equation (GPE) solver.
It was the primary project I worked on during my PhD and was primarily used to create 3D superfluid vortex structures via artificial magnetic fields.
My primary contribution to the project was the GPGPU knowledge to make the code performant on different hardware.
Though the code was written primarily in C++, a Julia version also exists.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
 

</feed>
